Jonathan Couch Papers 1839-1891 Mss.B.C831
American Philosophical Society
Jonathan Couch Papers
1839-1891
Mss.B.C831
American Philosophical Society
1.0 Linear feet
In many ways, Jonathan Couch was a prototype of the Victorian provincial naturalist, a trained physician whose eclectic, but intensely local interests ran from the life sciences to geology, Cornish folk beliefs, and local history. His major works included a three-volume translation of Pliny's Natural History (London, 1847-1849) published by the Wernerian Club of London, The History of Polperro (Truro, 1871), and the exhaustive four-volume A History of the Fishes of the British Islands (London, 1862-1868). The remnants of a wide-ranging mind, the Couch Papers contain a sampling of correspondence, rough drafts of articles, and notes on a variety of topics of interest to the Cornish naturalist and antiquarian, Jonathan Couch. The bulk of the correspondence relates to Couch's translation of Pliny's Natural History, published by the Wernerian Club of London between 1847 and 1849. The notes are highly diverse, but include some systematic descriptions of fishes, probably used in his A History of the Fishes of the British Islands and notes Cornish folk beliefs. Of particular interest are his "Notes connected with instinct and reason" and three manuscripts relating to evolutionism: "Enquiry into the circumstances...," "On the history and development of man," and "The Natural History of the Creation of the World, with its changes to the subsidence of the flood and Noah."
1 linear foot
Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870
Biographical/Historical note
In many ways, Jonathan Couch was a prototype of the Victorian provincial naturalist, a trained physician whose eclectic, but intensely local interests ran from the life sciences to geology, folk beliefs, and local history. The only child of Richard Couch and Phillipa Minards, Couch was born on March 15, 1789, at Polperro, a fishing village on the Cornish coast. After receiving a sound classical education at the Dame School and later at Bodmin Grammar School, Couch began a medical apprenticeship under Dr. John Rice of East Looe in 1803, and from 1808 to 1810, he completed his medical studies at the united St. Guy's and St. Thomas' Hospital in London. Returning to Polperro to practice medicine, Couch seldom again left Cornwall.
Despite the burdens of a busy medical practice, Couch began exploring an array of topics of antiquarian and natural historical interest from almost the moment of his return home. Bracketed by a profoundly local perspective, his interests ran the gamut from history and archaeology to Cornish folk beliefs, dialect, and the local flora and fauna. He became best known for his work on the life-blood of Polperro, its fisheries. Training the local fishermen to make natural historical observations and to assist him in bringing in rare specimens, Couch dissected and illustrated hundreds of fish over more than three decades of research, taking meticulous care to depict the colors of the live fish as accurately as possible. In recognition of his contributions, he was made a fellow of the Linnaean Society.
Couch was a regular contributor to several journals, including the Imperial Magazine, the Transactions and Proceedings of the Linnaean Society, and the Annals and Magazine of Natural History. His major publications include A Cornish Fauna (Truro, 1838, 1841), a three-volume translation of Pliny's Natural History (London, 1847-1849) published by the Wernerian Club of London, and the posthumously published The History of Polperro (Truro, 1871). His most important publication was the exhaustive four-volume History of the Fishes of the British Islands (London, 1860-1865), a seminal work that contained over 250 colored plates.
Thrice married, Couch was followed in medicine by all three of his sons, and his eldest son, Richard Quiller Couch, became a noted naturalist in his own right. Couch died in Polperro in 1870 at the age of 81.
Scope and Contents note
The remnants of a wide-ranging mind, the Couch Papers contain a sampling of correspondence, rough drafts of articles, and miscellaneous notes on a variety of topics of interest to Jonathan Couch, the Cornish naturalist and antiquarian. The bulk of the correspondence relates to Couch's translation of Pliny's Natural History, published by the Wernerian Club of London between 1847 and 1849. The notes are highly eclectic, but include some systematic descriptions of fishes, probably used in his A History of the Fishes of the British Islands and notes Cornish folk beliefs.
Of particular interest are Couch's "Notes connected with instinct and reason" (see also his "Habits of the diadem spider") and three manuscripts relating to evolutionism and human origins: "Enquiry into the circumstances...," "On the history and development of man," and "The Natural History of the Creation of the World, with its changes to the subsidence of the flood and Noah." Although somewhat fragmentary, his notes on dreams are a valuable complement to a similar manuscript held in the Linnaean Society of London.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired from Winifred Myers, 1980 (accn. no. 1980-1310ms).
Related Archival Materials note
The manuscript of Couch's Natural History of Cornish Fishes (1844) is held in the Kienbusch Angling Collection at Princeton University.
Couch's notebook of medical lectures, 1808-1847, kept during and after his study at Guy's and St. Thomas' Hospital in London, is housed in the Special Collections Deparment, Duke University Library.
Additional Couch manuscripts are located in the collections of the Linnaean Society of London.
Bibliography
Couch, Jonathan, A History of the Fishes of the British Islands, 4 vols. (London, 1877). Call no.: 597.0942 C83h v.1-4.
Couch, Bertha, Life of Jonathan Couch, FLS, etc., of Polperro, the Cornish Ichthyologist (Liskeard, 1891)
Tucker, Denys W., "A Cornish Ichthyologist in fact and fiction: 'Q' (Sir Arthur Quiller-Couch) on his Grandfather Jonathan Couch (1789-1870)" Society for the Bibliography of Natural History (1956): 137-151.
Early American History Note
This manuscript collection falls outside the geographic scope of the Early American guide (British North America and the United States before 1840). It may be of interest to scholars interested in global history, international relations, imperialism, or the U.S. in the world.
Cowper, B. Harris, (Benjamin Harris); Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882; Dunn, Matthias; Exeter, Jonathan; Fulcher, Thomas; Greenough, George Bellas, 1778-1855; Hardy, James; Herschel, John F. W., Sir, (John Frederick William), 1792-1871; Hocken, Edward Octavius; Moxon, Charles; Munford, George, 1794-1871; Peach, Charles William, 1800-1886; Pliny the Younger; Saunders, Robert; Slater, J. W., (John William); Sole, Edward; Watkins, Henry; Wernerian Club (London, England); Astronomy--Great Britain--18th century; Beyond Early America; Conchology--Great Britain; Cornwall--Description and travel; Creationism.; Developmental biology--Great Britain; Dreams; Evolution (Biology); Fisheries--Great Britain; Fishes--Great Britain; Human evolution; Instinct; Natural history--Great Britain--19th century; Pen works; Photographs; Superstition--Great Britain; Zoology--Great Britain
- Series I. Correspondence, 1839-1891; 47 folders
  - ADf to William Gladstone, n.d.; 1p.; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - ADf to Great Britain. Board of Trade. Commissioners, 1868 June 14; 1p.; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - ADf to Great Britain. Treasury. Lords Council, 1846 Sept. 6; 1p.; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - ADf to Mr. Wheelwright, 1861 March; 2p.; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1852 Dec. 27; 3p.; Couch, William (Box 1)
  - ALS to "Mr dear friend", 1891 Nov. 28; 3p.; Cowper, B. Harris, (Benjamin Harris) (Box 1)
  - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1866 June 15; 3p.; Dunn, Matthias (Box 1)
  - ALS Cy to Charles Godolphin, n.d.; 4p.; Exeter, Jonathan (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    In Couch's hand.
  - ALsS to Jonathan Couch, 1846; 2 items; Fulcher, Thomas (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Oct. 10; 2p.; Fulcher, Thomas (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Dec. 7; 2p.; Fulcher, Thomas (Box 1)
  - ALS to Charles Moxon, n.d.; 1p.; Greenough, George Bellas, 1778-1855 (Box 1)
    Probably originally enclosed in Moxon to Couch, 1846 October 2.
  - ALS to Jonathan Couch(?), n.d.; 4p.; Hardy, James (Box 1)
  - ALS to Charles Moxon, 1866 Dec. 26; 2p.; Herschel, John F. W., Sir, (John Frederick William), 1792-1871 (Box 1)
  - ALsS to Jonathan Couch, 1870, n.d.; 2 items; Hocken, Edward Octavius (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch(?), 1870 June 29; 4p.; Hocken, Edward Octavius (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch (incomplete), n.d.; 2p.; Hocken, Edward Octavius (Box 1)
  - ALsS to Jonathan Couch, 1846-1848; 55 items; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 March 10; 4p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 June 16; 4p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 June 22; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 October 2; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 October 8; 3p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 October 15; 3p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 October 17; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Nov. 5; 4p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Nov. 11; 3p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Nov. 14; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Nov. 26; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Dec. 2; 4p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Dec. 8; 3p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Dec. 10; 3p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Dec. 11; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Dec. 18; 4p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Dec. 26; 4p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Dec. 29; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Jan. 5; 4p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Jan. 14; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Jan. 20; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 March 30; 4p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 April 14; 3p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 April 27; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 May 26; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 June 7; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 June 8; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 June 18; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 June 21; 4p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 June 25; 3p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 July 1; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 July 7; 4p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 July 18; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 July 22; 4p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Aug. 10; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Sept. 3; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Sept. 6; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Sept. 15; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Sept. 22; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Oct. 27; 3p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Dec. 24; 3p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Jan. 1; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Jan. 21; 3p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 March 16; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 May 2; 3p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 June 2; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 June 14; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 July 23; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Sept. 2; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Sept. 5; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Oct. 19; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Nov. 11; 2p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Nov. 14; 1p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Dec. 6; 3p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, n.d.; 4p.; Moxon, Charles (Box 1)
  - ALsS to Jonathan Couch, 1846-1849; 17 items; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Nov. 12; 3p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Nov. 14; 3p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Nov. 25; 2p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Dec. 18; 1p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Dec. 21; 4p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1846 Dec. 30; 2p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Jan. 8; 1p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Jan. 16; 4p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1847 Nov. 10; 3p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 March 3; 4p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 June 16; 2p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 June 26; 2p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 June 27; 1p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Nov. 29; 4p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Dec. 6; 3p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1849 Jan. 24; 3p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1849 Feb. 27; 4p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, n.d.; 1p.; Munford, George, 1794-1871 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1844 March 28; 4p.; Peach, Charles William, 1800-1886 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1840 Feb. 28; 1p.; Saunders, Robert (Box 1)
  - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848; 2 items; Slater, J. W., (John William) (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Nov. 27; 1p.; Slater, J. W., (John William) (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Dec. 16; 1p.; Slater, J. W., (John William) (Box 1)
  - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1840 April 10; 4p.; Sole, Edward (Box 1)
  - ANS, n.d.; 2p.; Tregenna, Mr. (Box 1)
  - AMsS poem, "Sir Richard de Cotehele", 1839 April; 2 items (4p., 6p.); Trelawny, Anne (Box 1)
  - ALsS to Jonathan Couch, 1848-1849; 5 items; Watkins, Henry (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Jan. 18; 1p.; Watkins, Henry (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Jan. 31; 2p.; Watkins, Henry (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 April 30; 2p.; Watkins, Henry (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1848 Nov. 17; 2p.; Watkins, Henry (Box 1)
    - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1849 Feb. 19; 2p.; Watkins, Henry (Box 1)
  - Printed circulars, 1846-1849; 5 items; Wernerian Club (Box 1)
  - ALS to Jonathan Couch, 1861 Dec. 26; 4p.; Unidentified correspondent (Box 1)
- Series II. Essays and notes, 1855-1867; 82 folders (Box 1)
  - "Ancient British Church", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - Animals #1, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - Animals #2, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - Animals #3, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - "Axius Leach", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - "The Ballan wrasse", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - "Bp. Trelawny", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - "Borough of East Looe", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - "C. phasma", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - "Cataclysm", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - Chapel affairs, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - Charms, Misc., n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - "The connection of Natural Theology with Revelation", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - "Corkwing", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - "The cross buns of Easter", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - Death, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - Description of Polperro, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - "Development of crustacean animals" with "Decrease of the fisheries", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - "Dr. Clarke's comment -- Genesis", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 1)
  - Dreams, dreaming, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - Elections to Oxford, Cambridge, and Westminster, 1789-1796; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "An enquiry into the circumstances which are connected with the earlier phenomena of development in several species of animals, with reference also to the growth of plants", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Extract from naturalist's notebook no. 8", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Extracts from the Quarterly Review of Beeker's Gallus and Chariches: or private life of the Greeks and Romans," bound with "The wonders of the little world: or, a general history of man -- by Nath. Wanley, M.A. 1678", 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - Extracts: "Linnaeus dissertation on the sexes of plants -- translated by Sir James E. Smith," with "Ocean telegraphy -- by Dr. Wallich", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "The fairy mysis -- Missis Oberon; Mihi", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "The green-streaked wrasse", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Habits of the diadem spider," with "The little spider," and "Halibut" with "Salmon", 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Harbour crab", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Health of dwellings" with "Health of towns", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Horse", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Isaac Taylor's last testimony", 1867 Dec.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Language", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Lecture on ancient idolatry", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Lecture on the plagues of Egypt from the Egyptian point of view", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "List of the articles from the Royal wardrobe, granted by the first Queen Mary to the Lady Marquess of Exeter", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - List of words and definitions, 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Lucon's dialogue" with notes on the sunfish, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - McCaul, Alexander, "The old paths -- Modern Judaism compared with Moses and the prophets", 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Marcus Porcius Cato -- de re rustica", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Mechanics Institute", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - Misc. notes on Polperro, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Mr. Owen on the dodo", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Mysis", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Mysis chamaeleon", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Mysis Lamorna", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "The Natural History of the Creation of the World, with its changes to the subsidence of the flood and Noah" with misc. notes on various subjects, 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Notes connected with instinct and reason", 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Notes for circulation of the blood", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Notes from Dr. John Duris' Science of Christian Thought, with notes on fish", 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - Notes on ca.12 books, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - Notes on "Les observations de plusieurs singularités", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - Notes on Ovid, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - Notes on Pliny, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - Notes on several books, n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Notes on the natural history of the natterjack", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - Notes, misc., n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "On the history and development of man", 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Ovid, of the rust in corn", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Palinurus, Fabricius" and "Craw fish; red crab", 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Planner's lamprey" with "Notes on Atlantic Cable", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Polybius, Leach" with "Henslow's swimming crab", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Porcellana", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Prehistoric in Cornwall", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Process of development", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Recent speculations on primeval man -- by the Duke of Argyll" with "Primeval man", 1868 March; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "The red wrasse or three spotted wrasse", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "'Reign of law' in Fortnightly Review," signed by George Henry Lewes, 1867 July 1; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Retepora, Lamarck", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Scomberesox", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Septagint", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Sketch of a portion -- of a plot or all the Coast of Cornwall and Devonshire as they were fortified in 1588 against the landing of any enemy", 1 map, 33.3 x 20.9 cm; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
    Copied from an engraving made by T. Pine, 25 March 1740. As a local historian, Couch wrote a History of Polperro, published after his death. His comments on this map are specific, for Couch had to correct the geography.
    Other Finding Aids note
    Realms of Gold, 10 (1).
  - "Stenorhynchus, Lamarck" with "Long-legged spider crab" and "Slender spider crab", 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "The table crab", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Toads enclosed within the substance of the roots and bodies of trees", 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Unity of creation", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "A vindication of the probability of the story of Brutus, as related in the ancient history of Britain", 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Volcanoes of Auvergne", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Warburton's delegation", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - Weather observations, 1855; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)
  - "Woodcocks", n.d.; 1 folder; Couch, Jonathan, 1789-1870 (Box 2)